<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title></title>
		<link>http://localhost:4000</link>
		<atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>What's up in Nott's?</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; Nottingham's excellent tech scene and offerings. &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nottingham is a great place to be in tech, and not only because of the brilliant businesses and projects (&lt;a href=&quot;https://technation.techcityuk.com/cluster/nottingham/&quot;&gt;see the Tech Nation report from last year&lt;/a&gt;). It has a fantastic community and culture, as well as events and experiences to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of a few things that make Nottingham a great tech city in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meetups&quot;&gt;Meetups&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are currently over 30 tech meetups arranged in Nottingham. A list of the event and times can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://nottingham.digital/&quot;&gt;Nottingham.Digital&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 10%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2018-04-05/meetup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;step 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hackathons&quot;&gt;Hackathons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few hackathons around the midlands - including &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Hack Manchester&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Hack The Midlands&lt;/a&gt;. Nottingham now hosts a number of different hackathons, each with their own uniqueness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.govjam.org/content/about&quot;&gt;Notts GovJam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is happening on the 6th - 7th of June. The challenges of this hack is to find innovative solutions to problems faced by the public sector. As far as I’m aware, this is the first GovJam to be hosted in Nottingham. There are some fantastic people involved so it’s sure to be a fantastic event.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hacknotts.com/&quot;&gt;HackNotts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a hackathon for high school, undergraduate or postgraduate students, or graduates who are less than a year out of university. Hackathons are a great place and environment to learn. If you aren’t eligible to take part in the hack - that’s okay! Be a volunteer! You can soak up the fun of the event, help keep it running smoothly and meet some fantastic people making great projects.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://globalgamejam.org/&quot;&gt;Global Game Jam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; has already happened this year, in January. The focus of this event is for teams to make games with advice for some lead game developers. A theme is given out at the beginning of the event and sponsors make various tools available throughout the 48 hours. It’s not a competition, just a chance to have fun making something cool.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hack24.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Hack24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; has also already happened this year. I’ve written about it previously in my blog post &lt;a href=&quot;http://jesswhite.co.uk/hack242017-post/&quot;&gt;Hack24 ‘17, The Greatest Place On Earth&lt;/a&gt;, and as you can probably tell from that title alone it is very close to my heart. Sponsors set challenges for teams to take part in and compete to win challenges. The focus of the event isn’t the competition though. There is fantastic food, games, and general merriment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could write an entire post on all the great things about hackathons and the benefits of them. One day I might, but you should definitely try to experience one for yourself. You don’t need to be a developer! Just arrive wanting to have fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 10%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2018-04-05/hackathon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;step 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hackspaces&quot;&gt;Hackspaces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nottinghack.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Nottinghack&lt;/a&gt; is a fantastic hackspace. With the membership being based on a ‘Pay What You Think Is Right’ system​. There is a lot of equipment available including 3D printers, laser cutters, wool and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the equipment (with training on offer) there is a great community that attend Nottinghack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can attend just to hang out with like minded people, make something or attend a course and learn something new!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next workshop available from the date of this post is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://nottinghack.org.uk/introduction-to-arduino-workshop/&quot;&gt;Ardunio Workshops&lt;/a&gt; on Saturday 26th May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;podcasts&quot;&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to get involved in the tech scene, but aren’t too sure about the face-to-face aspect yet - how about checking out some of the local podcasts. There are a few about - but here are three you can start with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cynicaldeveloper.com/&quot;&gt;Cynical Developer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is probably the most technical of the three. Hosted by James Studdart - topics cover desktop, web and mobile development, mainly around the .Net Stack but often looking into other software and frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twineradio.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Twine Radio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - is hosted by Jonathan Relf. He talks with local meetup organisers and inflencencers about their events, what has happened and what is up ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twineradio.co.uk/&quot;&gt;BookClubPod&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; hosted on TwineRadio this is a brand new podcast. Jonathan Relf, Karl Bagci, Tom Jepson and I talk about some of the tech and non-fiction books we have read, what we think of them and how they influence our work. We plan to have guests in the future. It is a very relaxed podcast, just friends getting together and talking about their reads.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;code-club&quot;&gt;Code Club&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeclub.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Code Club&lt;/a&gt; is a remarkable organisation that runs free coding clubs for young people aged 9 - 13 years. It is completely volunteer lead and there are currently ~ 49 venues in Nottingham who have run a Code Club or intend to run one soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 6 venues are looking for a volunteer to help them get started so now is a great time to get involved as a volunteer. If you are considering starting a club in a venue near you there is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.futurelearn.com/courses/code-club&quot;&gt;a FREE online FutureLearn course called “Prepare to run a Code Club”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more info email : &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:eastmidlands@codeclub.org.uk&quot;&gt;eastmidlands@codeclub.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;workshops-and-other-fun-stuff&quot;&gt;Workshops and other fun stuff&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many places in Nottingham offering workshops and experiences to take part in. Some are technical - some are not. Here are a couple of places to check out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nearnow.org.uk/&quot;&gt;NearNow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; at Broadaway is a &lt;em&gt;‘studio for arts, design and innovation’&lt;/em&gt;. They hst workshops, events, galleries as well as providing fellowships for assisting making creative ideas become a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nottinghamcontemporary.org/&quot;&gt;Contemporary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; might seem a strange choice for a semi-tech focused list. A lot of great events and workshops are hosted here. There are DJ sets for gaming music, workshops to learn how to code or design… in fact it is so varied it is really hard to make a list. Check it out and find out what interesting things you can find.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 10%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2018-04-05/laugh.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;step 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;national-videogame-arcade&quot;&gt;National Videogame Arcade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot on offer at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenva.com/&quot;&gt;The National Videogame Arcade&lt;/a&gt;. Its well known for ALL THE GAMES but there are also workshops, events, corporate hire, parties and more. There are festival, events, and courses. They sometimes host designers, authors and programmers to come and talk about the cool work they have been involved in. There are are more interactive events and competitions to. There are more traditional learning experiences as well - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenva.com/pixelheads/&quot;&gt;PixelHeads&lt;/a&gt;, for example, provides courses for young people that are interested in learning how to code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such event that is returning this year (2018) is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenva.com/gamecity-festival/&quot;&gt;Game City Festival&lt;/a&gt;. It launched in 2006, and celebrates independent videogames and celebrating videogame culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;games&quot;&gt;Games&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit of a tangent away from tech related things - there are some great places to play games as well. Go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en-gb.facebook.com/thedicecup&quot;&gt;Dicecup&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;www.ludoraticafe.com/&quot;&gt;Ludorati&lt;/a&gt; to play boardgames or D’n’D. Both have very knowledgeable staff, refreshments and a WHOLE LOT of games. If you prefer something more digital - &lt;a href=&quot;https://en-gb.facebook.com/altgaminglounge/&quot;&gt;ALT&lt;/a&gt; might be more up your street. Again you can play alone, with friends or attend one of their many events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;community&quot;&gt;Community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why am I excited about all the above? What does it matter that there are all these fantastic things and why should you care?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I love most is the side effect of attending, learning, enjoying - which is the community that is built off the back of it. Through meeting people, having these experiences with them, you have something to talk about. You can find out about similar interests. This spreads and grows into this amazing ecosystem of people supporting each other, learning from each other and becoming friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made some of my closest friends through the events and community in Nottingham. It helped me believe I could enjoy tech and make it as a developer back when I hadn’t even started. It has provided support when it was needed. It has made me want to contribute myself by creating a meetup, mentoring others and speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please enjoy all the things that are “up in Notts” - and let me know about the things you find!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/whatsupinnotts-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/whatsupinnotts-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Changing your Google Adverts</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; Improve your online life. Change your targeted ads. &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-this-might-be-helpful&quot;&gt;Why this might be helpful&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google enables you to change your targeted adverts so you can indicate what you do and don’t want to see. There are numerous reasons why I think this is and amazing feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, there is gender targeted adverts. There are many sites that use this option. One example is Facebook. I have known many people who, fed up of seeing adverts related to dating sites and makeup because they have ticked the female box when signing up for a site, changed their settings to male so they could see tech and sports adverts instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a bigger reason why I think this is a great feature. There are many reasons why you might want to stop certain adverts displaying. I’ll use a personal example. As a 27 year old woman, for the last few years a lot of the adverts shown to me have been related to fertility, parenting and babies in general. Due to medical reasons, it’s ill advised for me to ever have children. This can sometimes be very difficult. Having the option to remove these adverts has been a big life improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons why you might not want to see certain adverts. Here’s a guide on how to change your Google ad’s to help make life a bit better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;steps-to-changing-your-adverts&quot;&gt;Steps to changing your adverts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go into your account settings. This can be done by clicking on your avatar in the far right corner and clicking on ‘My Account’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 10%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2018-02-18/step1.png&quot; alt=&quot;step 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click on Ad Settings and navigate to manage add settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 10%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2018-02-18/step2.png&quot; alt=&quot;step 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Here you can list the topics you like to see and those you don’t like to see.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 10%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2018-02-18/step3.png&quot; alt=&quot;step 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Here is what the list of topics looks like if you want to to remove parenting and babies from your targeted adverts. There is also the option of turning off targeted ad’s but I am not sure what the user experience would be like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 10%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2018-02-18/step4.png&quot; alt=&quot;step 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;and-thats-it&quot;&gt;And that’s it&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Googling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;here-is-the-reference&quot;&gt;Here is the reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.google.com/ads/answer/2662922?hl=en-GB&quot;&gt;Opt out of seeing personalised ads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/googleadsettings-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/googleadsettings-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Who Needs Dashboards?</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; An overview on the different forms of dashboards, what they are useful for and for whom.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-a-dashboard&quot;&gt;What is a dashboard?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dashboarding is part of the instrumentation portion of monitoring. The main purpose of a dashboard, no matter its type, is to enable the ability to quickly process information that a user might need. This may be to understand the current situation, to aide in decision making, or to inform that a reactive action is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://landing.google.com/sre/book/chapters/monitoring-distributed-systems.html&quot;&gt;Google SRE book&lt;/a&gt; dashboards are defined as following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“An application (usually web-based) that provides a summary view of a service’s core metrics. A dashboard may have filters, selectors, and so on, but is &lt;strong&gt;prebuilt to expose the metrics most important to its users&lt;/strong&gt;. The dashboard &lt;strong&gt;might also display team information&lt;/strong&gt; such as ticket queue length, a list of high-priority bugs, the current on-call engineer for a given area of responsibility, or recent pushes.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This description is probably aimed at the more ‘technical’ dashboards but there are two elements of this definition which support the definition just given which I have placed in bold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of common questions around dashboards including how long they should live and what should be on them. These questions aren’t going to be addressed in this post. Instead, we are taking a step back to examine what types of dashboards there are, what they are for, and who needs them. The following four categories of dashboard will be covered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business Intelligence (Strategic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Management Information (Tactical)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operational Information (Execution)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development Information (Execution)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m my opinion, dashboards are both beautiful and powerful. They come in many forms, each with their own strengths, purpose and evolution. I hope by the end, you will be considering who needs dashboards, and why, in your place of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;business-intelligence-dashboards&quot;&gt;Business Intelligence Dashboards&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Intelligence (BI) dashboards are also known as strategic dashboards. They contain information that show the overall health of a business and are used to help generate business strategy. There is a lot of number crunching and statistical analysis involved in working out if the business is making the right decisions and what future decisions need to be made. As such there is a lot of information that can be on a BI dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the responsibilities covered by BI dashboards include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measuring and monitoring trends that show how the business is performing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Shows if the current understanding of how the business is performing is accurate. This can help inform what kind of decisions need to be made.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparisons of the businesses performance over previous time frames.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Helps show any trends. If the business is under-performing, why? Has there been a trend like it previously and what did we do to mitigate it? Has there been a shift in performance over time?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measures demonstrating the accuracy of the statistical models used for giving a competitive advantage to their customer base.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Some companies have models of what a customer may need. For example, a gas company may expect higher income in winter months, especially in households with very young or elderly people. Are they selling their product at the right price? Are those that use their services likely to pay their bills?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BI dashboards answer the questions of &lt;em&gt;‘how is the business performing?’&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;‘what can be done to improve the performance?’&lt;/em&gt;. They can be used to help structure future business plans, monitor the health of the business and provide transparency to stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A business needs to meet goals and Key Performance Indicators (KPIs). An example is having quarterly goals to increase revenue or customer base. Dashboards can be useful for indicating a business’s progress to reaching these targets. For example, by showing real time achievement vs estimated progress that should have been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot that can be covered in BI dashboards. The best way to display this information or the information to be shown is a whole different topic for a different day. Today, we are covering who needs these dashboards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BI dashboards are needed by upper management including executives, managers and other corporate stakeholders. They need them to help make informed decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;management-information-dashboards&quot;&gt;Management Information Dashboards.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next there is Management Information (MI) dashboards. These contain information that can be used to measure the health of the business financially and the progress of initiatives to help reach the business goals. These are the statistics that cause the results shown on the BI dashboard. For example, MI dashboards may include monitoring of sales, losses or attendance. It can also cover how well a business is managing their costs while trying to increase their revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cost/profit balance is crucial to all businesses. Get it wrong, and the business won’t exist for long. Examples of data can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generated leads&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Money gained from each integrated third party&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of users or monetary gain for each type of product.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Results from marketing release or AB test&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Losses - temporary or permanent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cost of resource. This could be departmental costs from software required to salaries paid out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reported performance of competitors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Departments with a direct cost/profit impact such as marketing, finance, product and (in some businesses) data analytics need MI dashboards to guide the priority of current work, help to plan future work, and to monitor performance of previous work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dashboards are useful to these departments for numerous reasons. First of all it is a really accessible way to display a lot of information. For example, a marketing team may have a number of initiatives happening at one time and by using a dashboard they can see which initiatives appear to be having the biggest impact without sifting through Excel sheets of numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dashboards also make it easier to communicate what is going on to other areas of the business. If a product team have a dashboard displaying the number of customers, the type of product they are using, the business outgoings and incomings, and competitor performance it can not only help demonstrate the impact of the team, but direct their upcoming focuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mi-and-bi-are-closely-linked-what-happens-if-you-combine-the-two&quot;&gt;MI and BI are closely linked. What happens if you combine the two?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these types have their own uses and strengths. By combining the two, you can create a dashboard that’s of interest to an even wider audience. By having a combined BI/MI dashboard, a united vision on what the business is trying to achieve and their progress to that goal can be shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 10%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-10-25/MIBI.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;MI BI&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Above: A mock of a combined MI and BI dashboard.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pick a key KPI. This may be a financial goal, a number of users or something completely different that is expected to be achieved in a certain time frame. No matter what it is, work that is put forward to departments as a priority is normally guided in some way to achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By showing the progress in reaching the BI aim in a easy to understand format, everyone in the business can see the business’s health, it’s progress and how likely they are to get their bonus if it’s tied to performance. When I’ve seen this done the boundaries for the events shown on these dashboards are set by the business. Major events on the dashboard can include anything that can impact business in any way. Examples can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A marketing initiative.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new feature.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implementation of a new policy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outage of a third party.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integration with a new third party.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a combined MI/BI dashboard it is easy to the business’s progression towards it’s goal and the impact of ongoing work. Other high level statistics can be added to this board. For instance, I’ve seen examples where by hovering on a point you could see details such as estimated financial impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could also display the performance in a previous time frame. This can demonstrate temporal effects that might need to be planned for. An example would be Christmas for many companies. Some see a rise in use, others will find it a tougher time to make money in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good rules for MI/BI and business level dashboards: Keep it simple. Keep it high level. Keep it focused towards that one goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;execution-information&quot;&gt;Execution Information.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final two categories to be explored in this post are operational and development dashboards. These can be referred to as ‘execution information’ as they cover a lot of overlapping questions about how the business problem is tackled in a technical fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the questions they answer are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the health of the system?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Could it be better? (performance/stability)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If it’s unhealthy, what is broken or performing poorly?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is running?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where is the system most fragile?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operations is concerned with how a system runs on a production environment. This refers to the health and organisation of hardware and software. Development is concerned with the health of the software and how it is performing. This sometimes requires information about the hardware it is running on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on your company size and structure, these dashboards can also be combined and organised in different ways as both types of work are interlinked. Hardware and software can have a big impact on each other. Operational and development responsibilities can be, to some degree, interchangeable. The lines between the two are blurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some larger companies, the responsibilities can be split in a number of ways. There can be teams specialising in the operational information of hardware. There may be an SRE or software operations team that focuses its energy on the software’s capability to run in production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other companies take a more DevOps approach. Developers may have responsibilities regarding ensuring the readiness of software to run on production systems. This may include monitoring/fixing database read/write time, managing messaging queues, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all operational information is a concern of development, and not all development information is a concern to operations. The areas are so intertwined and are organised in such different ways it is difficult to write about them as separate entities. In the following will try to split them, but it’s worth noting that these aren’t a hard divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;operational-information&quot;&gt;Operational Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hardware-information&quot;&gt;Hardware Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operational dashboards covering hardware can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CPU&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RAM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disk Space - space, latency, read &amp;amp; write&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;software-information&quot;&gt;Software Information&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operational dashboards that cover software concerns may include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Database Read/Write times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;State of queueing technology i.e. partitions or the time to process a message&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SLA’s of third parties (internal or external) and whether they are being met&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Utilisation, saturation and error rates for services &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brendangregg.com/usemethod.html&quot;&gt;(USE)&lt;/a&gt;
-Rate of traffic, errors and duration of responses for API’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://peter.bourgon.org/blog/2016/02/07/logging-v-instrumentation.html&quot;&gt;(RED)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These demonstrate how and if a software system is coping with demand. As such, some of these may be covered by development dashboards as well. For instance, if software performance is a concern of a business’s development team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;development-information&quot;&gt;Development Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a developer, this final category to dashboarding I am exposed to a lot. For both operations and development, dashboarding has been used as a tool for a very long time. As such, there are a lot of different ways in which they can be used and structured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of some of the uses for development dashboards include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Monitoring the health of your system and aiding debugging issues&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;For checking whether the system is working or not. By being able to see what parts of the system are up, or what is behaving in a way that’s unexpected is imperative. A dashboard displaying the behaviour of each component can help speed up the process of diagnosing and fixing issues. This can be very helpful in pre-production as well as production environments to ensure the quality of software and improve its observability during testing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Performance monitoring&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;As mentioned, in some companies this may be an operational concern rather than a development one. Performance monitoring can be used to guide future work that improves the system, as well as demonstrating the effect of new pieces of work on the system. The more performant your product is, the smoother the experience for your user.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Guiding improvement&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Linked to the points above, a business can use monitoring to see where their software may need work. Again, this can either be an operational or development concern, or in some cases - both. Software systems can get old and creaky. They may be fit for purpose when first build, but like with anything in engineering, these systems need love and maintenance. Through monitoring you can see where bottlenecks are. Do you need to scale? Could the code do with another look at if it has not been touched in awhile? Are messages staying in the queues too long?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-needs-execution-information-dashboards&quot;&gt;Who Needs Execution Information Dashboards?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overlap in responsibilities for both types of execution teams, no matter their structure, means operational and development dashboards need to be available to all types of execution teams. Software and hardware are too intertwined and without having great communication between those responsible for those systems, everyone’s job gets harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally, if a company has a separate data team, they will want to see dashboards relating to the health and performance of their databases and the hardware the database is hosted on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also situations where product owners or stakeholders benefit from these dashboards too. This is more common is small businesses but I have seen examples of product using development information dashboards instead of having their own to see if SLA’s are being met for a third party for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of guiding improvement, the product team are also likely to be interested in a heads up if a particular feature or product is offering a poor customer experience or is showing signs of performance degradation. This can also be the case if the business are looking at pushing a particular feature which may need active work to support the demand of the increased customer uptake; otherwise this effort may not be accounted for in upcoming business plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, anyone who has a vested interest in how the system, software or hardware, is running needs dashboards with execution information displayed on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overall-who-needs-dashboards&quot;&gt;Overall, Who Needs Dashboards?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more categories of dashboard than those written about here, and even for those mentioned I could go into much more depth on who needs them and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, when done well, dashboards can make your life easier. They can help direct work. They help show the effects of your investment. They can improve communication and transparency in a business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also doesn’t hurt that they are easy to look at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This following quote from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Measuring-ITSM-Reporting-Management-Executives/dp/1490719458/ref=pd_cp_14_1?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&amp;amp;refRID=NERK3B79N4A24C5GJN7E&quot;&gt;Measuring ITSM&lt;/a&gt; sums up why everyone needs dashboards quite nicely&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If you don’t measure it, you can’t manage it” &lt;br /&gt;
“If you don’t measure it, you can’t improve it”&lt;br /&gt;
“If you don’t measure it, you probably don’t care”&lt;br /&gt;
“If you can’t influence it, then don’t measure it”&lt;br /&gt;
– &lt;em&gt;Randy A. Steinberg&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to make informed decisions you need a baseline and to measure progress. In order to fix or improve things, you need to be able to see when something is broken or can be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dashboards could be used to a further extent than what is covered in this post. How great would it be if thosse with direct customer contact had a dashboard of which parts of the product was down for maintenance or how many calls/emails were waiting? Or if sales had a board with their running totals versus aimed profit? Not only do dashboards make it easier to work with information, be reactive and plan well; but it can help increase openness and communication across business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who needs dashboards?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr style=&quot;border-top: dashed 1px;&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thank-you&quot;&gt;Thank you&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build upon my knowledge in these areas, I talked with a number of people who had worked with a variety of dashboards. My aim was to not only write from my own experience but to gather the uses of dashboards from different departments, different professions and different sized companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/darrenwhitworth1/&quot;&gt;Darren Whitworth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/michael-woodburn-609855/&quot;&gt;Michael Woodburn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/irutsun&quot;&gt;Karl Bagci&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jbjon&quot;&gt;Jonathan Relf&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/phr3nzii&quot;&gt;Chris Taylor&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/allmobro&quot;&gt;Moreton Brockley&lt;/a&gt; and anyone else who has encouraged my enthusiastic monitoring related babble. I now have enough information for a year’s worth of posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-further-reading&quot;&gt;Some Further Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scalyr.com/community/guides/zen-and-the-art-of-system-monitoring&quot;&gt;Zen and the Art of Systems Monitoring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geckoboard.com/blog/building-great-dashboards-6-golden-rules-to-successful-dashboard-design/#.WdKS62hSyUl&quot;&gt;6 Golden Rules to Successful Dashboard Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/davelavinsky/2013/09/06/executive-dashboards-what-they-are-why-every-business-needs-one/#25b577fe37d1&quot;&gt;Executive Dashboards - What they are and why every business needs one&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Measuring-ITSM-Reporting-Management-Executives/dp/1490719458/ref=pd_cp_14_1?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&amp;amp;refRID=NERK3B79N4A24C5GJN7E&quot;&gt;Measuring ITSM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@karlbagci&quot;&gt;Karl Bagci’s blog posts around ITSM &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://peter.bourgon.org/blog/2016/02/07/logging-v-instrumentation.html&quot;&gt;Peter Bourgon - Logging v. Instrumentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brendangregg.com/usemethod.html&quot;&gt;Brendan Gregg - USE Method&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://landing.google.com/sre/book/chapters/monitoring-distributed-systems.html&quot;&gt;Google SRE book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hbs.edu/faculty/Publication%20Files/10-036.Pdf&quot;&gt;From Strategy to Business Models and to Tactics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2015/03/defining-strategy-implementation-and-execution&quot;&gt;Defining Strategy, Implementation, and Execution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/whoneedsdashboards-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/whoneedsdashboards-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Implementing Instrumentation For Business Need</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; A proposed approach on how to make the most of instrumentation, and how to unite the development and business overview of products. Mostly opinion, but this has been applied at work to test the theory.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monitoring is an expansive topic which I have gained a strong interest in this year. How to effectively log, instrument and alert is discussed at length and there seems to be no one true answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog, the problems that have been faced with instrumentation on a personal level are discussed. The means of how we attempted to solve these issues and the result of the implementation are also explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of different types of and uses for instrumentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For monitoring the health of a system&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The health of a system refers to what is up, down and what errors are being thrown. This is most useful for developers. It can be used for diagnostics and for seeing what they need to fix, where and if there are effects downstream. This is especially powerful in combination with operational dashboards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also be used to monitor the health of third parties. A certain endpoint becoming unavailable can result in a number of problems. For example, in terms of a customer’s experience of a website, the customer may be shown an error screen or a long loading time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Measuring operational information&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Operational information informs about the day to day running of a system. This information is useful both to developers and the rest of the business. For developers, this information can be used to spot weaknesses in the system or to detect when issues start to occur. The performance and health of the system is the very minimal amount of monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Analysing metrics for business use&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Metrics can be used in two ways for business use. They can be used for MI (Management Information) or BI (Business Intelligence) purposes. BI is where useful data is shown in a way that the business will understand so that it can be used to inform business strategy. On the other hand, MI is information that can be used to measure the health of the business financially. This can include monitoring of sales, losses or attendance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the work discussed here, the dashboards created were more for the purposes of BI. By creating dashboards that the business could understand, they could work out where work needed to be done to improve their products and features. For example, a dashboard could show the effectiveness of sms versus email for your customers. The uptake of these communication methods could then direct the aims of a marketing team and how they tell customers about their next initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are MI style dashboards at the company. They show profit / loss across time, with major events bookmarked on the dashboard. Major events can include an outage, a promotion or a new feature; anything that may have a big impact on the financials of a company. They are very useful, but are part of another piece of work. The reason for why MI is treated separately from BI here will become apparent later in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-issues-faced&quot;&gt;The issues faced&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My early experience with instrumentation had been dashboards built purely by developers. They decided the metrics to be measured and what was to be shown. These were primarily used for diagnosing the health of a system and to determine what needed to be alerted upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues with this method were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Noisy dashboards&lt;/em&gt;: In some cases dashboards contained unnecessary information. This made them busy and hard to read. Sometimes they would be trimmed down, but often this wasn’t the case.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Missing information&lt;/em&gt;: In other situations the dashboards did not contain the information needed to spot problems early on.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neglected dashboards&lt;/em&gt;: Dashboards were used in the short term. Once the feature was considered stable, they were only really used if considered useful for diagnosing the cause of an alert.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full power of instrumentation wasn’t being utilised. To address this we had a look into how dashboards can be useful to the business as a whole. Some of the reasons we use dashboards include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Observing features are behaving as expected.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Observing the health of a feature.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checking SLA’s are being adhered to.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being able to identify where problems are arising with ease.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identifying areas to be optimised.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned dashboards are useful not only to development teams, but also to other departments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-proposed-solution&quot;&gt;The proposed solution&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company works in scrum. As such, work is discussed between stakeholders, then is prioritised based on business need. It is organised into epics (large themes of work) which are split into stories. Each of these stories have acceptance criteria which outline the expected results of each piece of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the information we need on the dashboards align closely to the acceptance criteria driving feature development. As mentioned, part of the purpose of the acceptance criteria of epics and stories is to outline the stakeholders expectations of what behaviours features should have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can align some of the acceptance criteria to outline what metrics are useful for business use and operational information. The instrumentation for the health of the system can be left to the developers. By building metrics and dashboards from acceptance criteria we ensure that stakeholders questions can be answered regarding expected behaviours and contracts with third parties. Further, it restricts the information to what is useful to those using the dashboards, decreasing unnecessary noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier, metrics for business use were discussed in terms of MI (Management Information) and BI (Business Intelligence). The reason this work encompasses BI dashboards but not MI is that the information needed for BI aligns up more with what can be acquired from acceptance criteria i.e. how many customers use X feature. The information for MI (i.e. financial information) is not normally gained from the development teams. As such, it would not align well to being part of acceptance criteria and is treated as a separate stream of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing all of this we can make a couple of different types of dashboards for projects. The first type shows operational and health metrics from which alerts can be based. The second are business metric dashboards for other teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Health and operational metrics&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
When features are first released, dashboards are monitored closely by development and are incredibly useful. Further, when there are alerts showing something has gone wrong in the system, dashboards are useful for quick diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Business metrics&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If the dashboards are built from acceptance criteria, we could provide access to the dashboards to teams the features matter to. This makes it more likely for abnormal behaviour to be spotted. The core stakeholders for a feature are more likely to recognise unusual behaviour early. These behaviours can also be alerted on if they are signifiers of potential problems in the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-application&quot;&gt;The application.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To try this theory out, first we had to get buy in from the business. The product owner was required to write extra acceptance criteria in order for this to work. They needed to get requirements from the stakeholders about what they needed to know about each feature and about agreed contracts with any third parties involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once gained, the product owner included acceptance criteria for instrumentation covering these requirements. By doing this it ensured that these metrics would be included as part of the development work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-results&quot;&gt;The results.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process has been followed for a couple of projects now. In our case, it has worked very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first project was a back-end feature integrating with a third party. The dashboard was shared with development and another department. It enabled both teams not only to spot bugs easily but also react to unusual behaviour. Further, we could answer questions about response times with the third parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By driving our dashboards through business need, they are evolving in a way that benefits developers and stakeholders. They are being viewed by those who need to see them and they have information that is useful to both parties. Instrumentation is no longer a second class citizen and is being utilised again. Another useful benefit is that this has lead to greater transparency across departments and has given us a unified view of the products we are delivering. This in turn has lead to improved collaboration all round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By no means do I think this is the right solution for all business’. Indeed I believe there is still a lot to learn and room for improvement in our implementation. Nonetheless, it has been undeniably useful in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been some challenges with this approach. First of all was getting the buy in from the business and getting the other teams to see how dashboards could be useful to them. Honestly, I still don’t think we utilise the full power yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the downside that it takes developer time to put this instrumentation in place. Though it is minimal per story, and has led to us avoiding some problems we would have missed otherwise, it does add up over time. But I would argue this has been more than saved by the sheer number of live issues or bugs averted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other issue we are yet to solve is how long a dashboard is important enough to us that we need it on our screens every day. There are screens around the office with important information. Finding the balance for how long the dashboard needs to be on our main screens after the initial release is still a balance we are reaching. Until it’s stable? But how long is that? Currently the screen changes when the next big release goes out, but it is still too early to say if this is right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having project focused dashboards has proved useful on initial release and for debugging off the back of an alert. Even when the dashboards aren’t on the main screens, they are easily reachable. Instrumentation is incredibly useful for spotting where in the system something has gone wrong, whether an alert is actually due to a upstream problem and therefore where you should focus your investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, we have had work produced off the back of having business driven dashboards. So far two departments in particular have embraced this approach to instrumentation and have based work off the back of patterns they have seen through metrics they have helped to drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-future-of-this-project&quot;&gt;The future of this project.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These dashboards have been built using existing software, and as we move to using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elastic.co/&quot;&gt;Elastic&lt;/a&gt; stack and its increased functionality, there is a lot more we can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim is to eventually build team specific dashboards as well as feature specific dashboards. For example, it would be great if the sales or customer service teams had a dashboard they could understand that shows when certain features of the website goes down. They could then be trained on how to respond when these outages occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways in which this work could develop and grow. It’s an area I could discuss at length and that’s exactly what I’m going to do in a future blog post…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/instrumentationforbusiness-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/instrumentationforbusiness-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Goodbye WIT &amp; Thank You</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; A look back at my time founding and organising Women In Tech Nottingham after handing over the reigns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women In Tech Nottingham had it’s first event in April of last year. It had taken months of discussions with sponsors, venues, organising social accounts, meeting potential speakers, getting advice from current meetup organisers. This has all come together for the first in many events I would go on to organise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jesslynnrose&quot;&gt;Jess Rose&lt;/a&gt; was the star of the show. She gave a fantastic talk on Imposter Syndrome, capturing many hearts and minds. After her talk, those who attended wrote on post its about what they wanted from the event. I was so stressed throughout the whole thing to be honest, it is still a blur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following 15 months I hope I have met most of the hopes written on those post-its.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole experience has been an adventure. I have been involved in things I never could have dreamed, met amazing people and even grown personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:50%; margin-left: 20%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KBAMsqBzViI&quot; title=&quot;About Women In Tech Nottingham&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-07-06/youtube.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Youtube Video&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To the members of WiTNotts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for the adventure. Without your support Women In Tech Nottingham would never have become what it is. I will still be attending the event, though I will not be organising any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have enjoyed getting you know all, and hearing about all the amazing things you’ve been getting up to. I hope that we remain friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please continue to give Women In Tech your full love and support. Keep going to the various tech events in Nottingham. Help our fantastic tech community blossom to its full potential. The community is nothing without the people involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s happened in the past 15 months&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve had some amazing speakers. Thank you to everyone who has taken part and wowed us with their talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Event&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;06/04/2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jesslynnrose&quot;&gt;Jess Rose&lt;/a&gt; : Imposter Syndrome&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;04/05/2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MultiPie&quot;&gt;Annie Haley&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/epixmedia&quot;&gt;Zoe Easey&lt;/a&gt;: Startups&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;01/06/2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Tech_Geek_Girl&quot;&gt;Liz Hardwick&lt;/a&gt;: Boosting Productivity&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;01/07/2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/crocstar&quot;&gt;Christine Cawthorne&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LittleHelli&quot;&gt;Helen Clark&lt;/a&gt;: Content and Design&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;01/09/2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lexicobob&quot;&gt;Alex Roberts&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ruthmills&quot;&gt;Ruth Mills&lt;/a&gt;: IoT &amp;amp; Makers&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;06/10/2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/primaryicttech&quot;&gt;Katharine Childs&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/chloe_cheeseman&quot;&gt;Chloe Cheeseman&lt;/a&gt;: Volunteering Tech&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;03/11/2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GeorginaWilcox&quot;&gt;Georgina Wilcox&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RedRoxProjects&quot;&gt;Amy Dickens&lt;/a&gt;: Postmortem Culture at Google &amp;amp; Pathway To Proms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;01/12/2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Holiday Special with soldering from Nottinghacks&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;01/12/2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LittleHelli&quot;&gt;Helen Clark&lt;/a&gt; joined as a co-organiser&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;02/02/2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LittleHelli&quot;&gt;Helen Clark&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mairperkins&quot;&gt;Mair Perkins&lt;/a&gt;: Hack24 &amp;amp; Animation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;02/03/2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/weareunstuck&quot;&gt;Sarah King&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Samathy_Barratt&quot;&gt;Samathy Barrat&lt;/a&gt;: Small Business Acting Bigger &amp;amp;  Neo4J Graph&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;05/03/2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Showing of Hidden Figures for International Womens Day raises £170 for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CodeClubEMids&quot;&gt;Code Club&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;18/03/2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Two Women In Tech Teams take part in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hack24.co.uk/#intro&quot;&gt;Hack24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;06/04/2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/HelenaWootton&quot;&gt;Helena Wootton&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SamanthaJDeakin&quot;&gt;Samantha Deakin Hill&lt;/a&gt;: Personal Data Protection &amp;amp; Start Experiencing&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;04/05/2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gosiaborzecka&quot;&gt;Gosia Borzecka &lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/anna_hax&quot;&gt;Anna Dodson&lt;/a&gt;: Sharepoint &amp;amp; Browser Security&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;01/06/2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rvedotrc&quot;&gt;Rachel Evans&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/paulineroche&quot;&gt;PaulineRoche&lt;/a&gt;: Tech For Good &amp;amp; Destruction, Decapods and Doughnuts&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;02/07/2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Lowry_83&quot;&gt;Claire Lowry&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheSimplifiers&quot;&gt;Mary Baird-Wilcock&lt;/a&gt;: How to stop the glorification of BUSY &amp;amp; Agile&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these events we helped voluntary groups find volunteers, raised money for charity, helped school kids find work placements, taken part in careers fairs, along with building a fantastic community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How you have changed me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Women in Tech I was a rather introverted student who had some exposure to the tech community through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hack24.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Hack24&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.technottingham.com/&quot;&gt;Tech Nottingham&lt;/a&gt;. I was terrified about speaking in public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, though I am still very nervous about public speaking, I think I am getting better at speaking in front of crowds. Talking to strangers and getting to know them is now enjoyable. Finally I have learnt more about the amazing community in technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meetup has helped me mature, has taught me a lot about organisation and the many intricacies in managing an organisation at a small scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking to the future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LittleHelli&quot;&gt;Helen Clark&lt;/a&gt; is going to continue the Women In Tech legacy. Now that the meetup is partnering with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.technottingham.com/&quot;&gt;Tech Nottingham&lt;/a&gt; I’m looking forward to it growing and doing great things. I only ever intended to run the meetup for 12 months. For it to truly represent our community, it needed to be taken over by a new person. I love Women In Tech Nottingham, but I am far to close to it. It is time for change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The merging of brands between the meetup and conference is also a great thing. Saves a lot of confusion and I really think both organisations can help each other. It’s going to be a fantastic mutual partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for me, I’ll still be about. I will be attending as many of the events as I can as well as many of the other fantastic meetups in Nottingham. I am going to spend the time I used to use on WiT on studying. Also, I am going to practice what I have preached many times over the last year. I am going to give speaking a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, it’s been a fun ride. I am grateful to you all and will be forever supporting WiT from the sidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never forget to be excellent to each other, and party on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:50%; margin-left: 20%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-07-06/billandted.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Be Excellent&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/goodbyewit-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/goodbyewit-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>NDC Oslo 2017</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A summary of my time as a volunteer at NDC Oslo 2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:50%; margin-left: 20%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-06-19/sticker.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sticker&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-it-began&quot;&gt;How it began&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having a brilliant time volunteering at NDC London earlier this year (&lt;a href=&quot;http://jesswhite.co.uk/2017-01-29/ndclondon-post/&quot;&gt;blog post here&lt;/a&gt;) I snatched the chance to volunteer at Oslo. Moreton and I booked our flights and hotel, packed our bags and headed to Norway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke at 3am and after travelling on many trains, planes and automobiles, finally arrived in Oslo, the birth place of NDC. After a quick snack it was time to find out more about what being a volunteer would involve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:50%; margin-left: 20%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-06-19/badge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Badge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a tour of the venue (which was GIGANTIC compared to London), we were put to work: unpacking lanyards and hoodies ready for the following day. There were a few familiar faces that were good to catch up with and we met a few people we would become friends with over the following days. After working up a sweat, and collecting our badges, we all went home for some well earned sleep .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-day&quot;&gt;First Day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7.45am all the volunteers gathered for the very first day of the conference. Moreton and I were on badge duty - he scanned tickets &amp;amp; I passed out the printed badge labels. It was great fun seeing a mixture of excited and jet lagged faces entering the conference. Though we had some technical difficulties, we were done with plenty of time to see the Keynote by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dylanbeattie&quot;&gt;Dylan Beattie&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking in to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dylanbeattie/status/868846378151284736&quot;&gt;I Want My NDC &lt;/a&gt;, feeling the buzz from the attendees, it was hard not to get excited. Dylan is a fantastic speaker if you want to both laugh and cogitate. He was a fantastic choice for Keynote and did not disappoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was working Room 1 the morning of the first day. The first talk was &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/building-a-serverless-eventsourced-slack-clone/&quot;&gt;Building a Serverless, EventSourced Slack clone by Andy Davies&lt;/a&gt; and the second &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/serilog-instrumentation-that-works-for-you/&quot;&gt;Serilog: Instrumentation that Works for You by Nicholas Blumhardt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a big fan of Serilog and of Nicholas’ blog. At work I’ve been working on a centralised logging project using Serilog and Elastic Stack. As such I was thrilled to see him speak, and was not let down. It was very lucky that I got assigned that room as my first one of NDC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The afternoon I was off duty and chose to watch &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/data-magic-with-the-elastic-stack/&quot;&gt;Data magic with the Elastic stack! by Aleksander Stensby&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/building-resilient-applications-in-microsoft-azure/&quot;&gt;Building Resilient Applications In Microsoft Azure by Scott Allen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/getting-realtime-with-akka-net-react-and-redux/&quot;&gt;Getting real(time) with Akka.NET, React and Redux by Francis Paulin&lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/life-liberty-and-the-pursuit-of-apiness-the-secret-to-happy-code/&quot;&gt;Life, Liberty and the Pursuit of APIness : The Secret to Happy Code by Dylan Beattie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Nicholas’, Aleksander’s and Dylan’s talks I was buzzing about monitoring &amp;amp; the power of Elastic. I was ready to get back into the swing of my work and it re-lit the fire of this particular passion. It has been a fantastic first day, and what’s a better way to top it of than with a boat cruise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;boat-cruise&quot;&gt;Boat Cruise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beautiful sunshine, ~200 NDC attendees boarded on two boats to enjoy a shrimp feast, each others company and the view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:90%; margin-left: 8%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-06-19/boat.png&quot; alt=&quot;Boat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you go to NDC, do the cruise. We had an amazing time. I laughed so much my sides ached (I’m blaming Todd for a lot of that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;second-day&quot;&gt;Second Day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second day, I had the afternoon shift. After a little lie in to get over the lack of sleep from travelling. First of all we went to see &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/scaling-docker-containers-using-kubernetes-and-azure-container-service/&quot;&gt;Scaling Docker Containers using Kubernetes and Azure Container Service by Ben Hall&lt;/a&gt;. I use Docker at work, and Moreton wanted to learn more. Ben Hall is an excellent speaker when you want to learn about Docker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this we went to watch &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/doing-devops-as-a-politically-powerless-developer/&quot;&gt;“Doing Devops” as a politically powerless developer by Damian Brady&lt;/a&gt;. This is enlightening if you want to know how to more about convincing your company / helping your team to work in a devops way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, I was the volunteer for Room 1. One of the great things about volunteering is that you see talks you wouldn’t have necessarily seen. In the case of that particular afternoon I saw &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/keeping-the-noisy-neighbors-happy/&quot;&gt;Keeping the Noisy Neighbors Happy by Eran Stiler&lt;/a&gt; which is a talk on multi-tenancy - a subject I knew nothing about. This was followed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/tba-8/&quot;&gt;It’s NDC - But Not As We Know It&lt;/a&gt; - an entertaining and educational panel discussion for the masses. Finally I saw &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/the-web-lands-in-the-virtual-and-mixed-realities/&quot;&gt;The Web lands in the Virtual and Mixed Realities by Maximiliano Firtman&lt;/a&gt; which was a great overview of current VR technologies. This is again another area I know little about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;party&quot;&gt;Party&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year was the 10th Anniversary of NDC Oslo, and the party was worthy of it. First came out a cake large enough to feed all the attendees. In other words - bloody big cake. There was plenty of food and drink dotted around the main arena including the beer brewed by &lt;a href=&quot;www.twitter.com/benwholikesbeer&quot;&gt;Ben&lt;/a&gt;. I personally went for meat and cheese, including my very first taste of elk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first piece of organised entertainment were the failure tales. Some of the speakers presented times when they really thought they had fecked up, or a time of a mistake. All the stories were entertaining, and some had educational points. I love this part of the NDC party as these people who have spoken with such great authority and gained our awe, suddenly appear very human. It’s good to remember that nobody is perfect even if they can live demo flawlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you had the option of taking part in the pub quiz. I watched from afar with my other half this time. We tried to answer by ourselves but soon realised the quiz was for the big leagues. Its bloomin’ hard!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:50%; margin-left: 20%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-06-19/concert.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Party&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close the party, a local band called Love Shack performed. They cover 80’s songs and it was a lot of fun head-banging to Metallica, screeching to ACDC and acting like an idiot to Cyndi Lauper. As the final song played, we snuck off tired &amp;amp; happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;last-day&quot;&gt;Last Day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, the final day of NDC was a tad slow for me. We had met one of the speakers, Martin, on the boat cruise previously. He’s a genuine and lovely guy so both Moreton and I decided to go see him speak. Very glad we did. His talk &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/sensors-data-and-dashboards-azure-iot-end-to-end/&quot;&gt;Sensors, data and dashboards: Azure IoT end-to-end by Martin Abbott&lt;/a&gt; was brilliant and gave a superb overview of using IoT with Azure, even though the demo gods didn’t listen to his prayers. Oh cruel demo gods!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the morning I decided to do some work on a project I currently have on the go. My hands were itching to get back on a keyboard and I was booked in to volunteer for the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again there was some variety with the talks in the room I was covering. The first was &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/rest-3-0-a-lap-around-http-apis-next-generation/&quot;&gt;ReST 3.0 – A lap around HTTP Apis’ next generation by Sebastien Lambla&lt;/a&gt; which was useful to my day to day. This was followed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/fake-paket/&quot;&gt;FAKE + Paket – PowerTools for .NET developers by Steffen Forkmann&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://ndcoslo.com/talk/servant-web-apis-at-the-type-level/&quot;&gt;Web APIs at the Type Level by Erlend Hamberg&lt;/a&gt;. Both were very new topics to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the venue having mostly wrapped up, the volunteers were asked to help pack some of the stuff away. Happy to oblige, we collected voting cards and boxes, carried barrels and trees, packed away table cloths and cats, along with a few other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After such hard work, all of us needed a well deserved drink - so off to &lt;a href=&quot;www.twitter.com/PubConf/&quot;&gt;Pubconf&lt;/a&gt; we went!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pubconf&quot;&gt;PubConf&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer - I have only been to 2 NDC’s now BUT PubConf is probably my favourite part of the full 3 days.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was Moreton’s very first Pubconf, and the poor boy had to put up with me buzzing about it since NDC London. I was a little concerned I had over-hyped it, but even he agrees it’s brilliant. It was better than he expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to break the second rule of Pubconf too much (&lt;em&gt;What Happens At Pubconf Stays At Pubconf&lt;/em&gt;, the first being &lt;em&gt;Don’t Be An Asshole&lt;/em&gt;). If you go to NDC anywhere &lt;em&gt;GO TO PUBCONF&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You’ll laugh. &lt;strong&gt;You’ll drink beer&lt;/strong&gt; to help your dry throat. &lt;br /&gt;
You’ll cry (from more laughter). &lt;strong&gt;You’ll drink beer&lt;/strong&gt; to rehydrate.&lt;br /&gt;
You’ll sing. &lt;strong&gt;You’ll drink beer&lt;/strong&gt; to help you reach that high note.&lt;br /&gt;
You’ll talk to amazing people. &lt;strong&gt;You’ll drink beer&lt;/strong&gt; for fuel.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You’ll drink beer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;www.twitter.com/toddhgardener&quot;&gt;Todd&lt;/a&gt; is King of Pubconf and for that - he is king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-finish&quot;&gt;To Finish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NDC Oslo did not disappoint. Both Moreton and I are already making plans to be at NDC London next year. We met great people, learnt new things and created memories. If you get the chance to go to any of the NDC’s as an attendee or as a volunteer - DO IT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to all of you who made our NDC Oslo fantastic. There are too many to name but you all know who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special shout out to &lt;a href=&quot;www.twitter.com/jakbradf&quot;&gt;Jackob&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;www.twitter.com/charlottelyng&quot;&gt;Charlotte&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;www.twitter.com/KjerstiSandberg&quot;&gt;Kjersti&lt;/a&gt; for letting us be involved / volunteer at your amazing event. Especially Kjersti - without you, we still wouldn’t know how to eat shrimp.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/ndcoslo2017-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/ndcoslo2017-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Hack Yourself First Day</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A team day at work to learn more about security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our resident shady coder Jordan, organised an epic hack day at Oakbrook to teach us a thing or two about hacking and 
security. For the first half of the day we were given a list of tools we could investigate. These were both to hack and 
for helping to make apps more secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 8%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-04-05/hacker.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hack&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second half of the day, we played capture the flag. Jordan hosted two versions of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.troyhunt.com/&quot;&gt;Troy Hunts&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackyourselffirst.troyhunt.com/&quot;&gt;Hack Yourself First&lt;/a&gt; website with a nifty scoreboard of vulnerabilities. We were split into 2 teams, and 
were awarded points for successful attacks and pre-emptive defence against certain attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This day wasn’t just for fun. It was to open our eyes to many security issues we wouldn’t otherwise have considered. But… IT 
WAS REALLY FUN!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;first-half&quot;&gt;First Half&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a couple of products I took time to investigate. Here is the overview of the opinions I had formed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;acunetix&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acunetix.com/blog/docs/acunetix-quick-start-guide/&quot;&gt;Acunetix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first product I explored on the first half of the day, and I’m not ashamed to say I fell in love.
Acunetix is used to scan and detect vulnerabilities on a site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only use the free version of this product - but was really impressed with its features. When conducting a scan 
any vulnerabilities found during its progress were displayed so that you don’t have to wait for the final reports 
for the results. There are different levels of error, so it is clear which are urgent and which are a lower risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another feature, which I found especially exciting, is that when a scan is complete there were a choice of reports that could 
be produced. an OWASP report, compliance level report, dev level report - these were but a few of the options. These are 
produced in a format that has information suitable for the needs of those who are going to receive it. For example, the dev 
report says the vulnerability, the level and guidance on where it could be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pros:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;+ Nice UI
+ Real time feedback
+ Lots of scanning options
+ Different formats of reports can be produced
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cons:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;- Scanning is pretty slow
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;others&quot;&gt;Others&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oxid.it/cain.html&quot;&gt;Cain &amp;amp; Abel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/laramies/theHarvester&quot;&gt;Harvester&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.metasploit.com/&quot;&gt;Metasploit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I couldn’t test out any of the above. Between anti-viruses and firewalls
I couldn’t even get a couple of them to download onto my machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;capture-the-flag&quot;&gt;Capture The Flag&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained in the introduction, we were split into two teams to play capture the flag.
Our team split into 3 parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attackers: attacked the site using tools such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://sqlmap.org/&quot;&gt;SQLmap&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defenders: fixed vulnerabilities in the site.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Testers: Found weakness’ in the teams site to fix, and the opposing teams site to attack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a tester in this team, which gave me a good chance to put Acunetix to the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This game was great fun - and I really hope Jordan presents it at a meetup near you. His scoring
table was nifty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This day was not just for entertainment but also for learning. It has certainly met that purpose. 
A lot of us felt that not only did we learn a lot on the day, but also learnt about how little we knew
 about the topic of security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of what we took from the day will go on to be applied in our site. It has definitely inspired others to 
do the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pluralsight.com/courses/hack-yourself-first&quot;&gt;hack yourself Pluralsight course&lt;/a&gt; to learn a bit more about this vast topic.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/hackyourselffirst-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/hackyourselffirst-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Hack24 '17, The Greatest Place On Earth</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A summary of Hack24 2017. Also, a love letter to Hack24.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-tech-life-and-tech-notts&quot;&gt;My Tech Life and Tech Notts.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.technottingham.com/&quot;&gt;Tech Nottingham&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hack24.co.uk&quot;&gt;Hack24&lt;/a&gt; and the people involved are incredibly close to my heart. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/allmobro&quot;&gt;Moreton&lt;/a&gt; (my taller half) took me to Tech Nottingham before I even
 started my Computer Science course. I think this was partly to get me inspired but also so that I could meet people and the tech world didn’t feel so daunting and scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after that I was attending the first Hack24. It’s strange to think my life in tech has been pretty much documented by Hack24 photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 8%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-03-24/3years.png&quot; alt=&quot;3 Years&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even what is now a massive part of my life, &lt;a href=&quot;www.womenintechnotts.co.uk&quot;&gt;Women In Tech Nottingham&lt;/a&gt; (WITNOTTS), would not have happened if it weren’t for the Sewards. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MrAndrew&quot;&gt;Andrew&lt;/a&gt; is the one who talked me into creating a safe space to encourage more people into the social part of our fine tech community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking of, just under a year ago I did an interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jbjon&quot;&gt;Jonathan&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://twineradio.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Twine Radio&lt;/a&gt; talking about the plans I had for it at the time. I stated that I wanted the group to have a presence at Hack24 in 2017. At the time I had no idea that this could be a real possibility, it was a pipe dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think that brings us nicely to this years hack…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hack24-2017&quot;&gt;Hack24 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we fast forward to last weekend. WITNOTTS is no longer a solo burden of love, but I now have &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LittleHelli&quot;&gt;Helen Clark&lt;/a&gt;. Helen has been an absolute god send over the last few months. We have both grown up with Hack24, coming on leaps and bounds over the last 3 years. We both love the Tech Nottingham community and do our best to get more people involved. She really drives a lot of the work we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We mentioned to Hack24 that we wanted to bring a team of our member to the event and they very  kindly donated 8 tickets to WITNOTTS for this year. 
Enough for two whole teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team Wild Garlic, Basil, Olive Oil, Pine Nuts &amp;amp; a Pinch of Salt &amp;amp; Pepper:&lt;/em&gt; Amy Dickens, Maria Digregorio, Bety Mehide &amp;amp; Alexa Spors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team Totally Triumphant Bodacious Babes:&lt;/em&gt; Helen Clark, Elsa, Jessica White &amp;amp; Laura Rossi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both teams came to the event with the aim of having fun. It’s safe to say we achieved that! The ladies were fully supportive of each other constantly making sure that the others were doing okay and having a laugh. Even if many of Elsa’s laughs were directed at the face I make when I’m concentrating. (Don’t worry Elsa - I still think you are awesome!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:40%; margin-left: 30%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-03-24/beteo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stickers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WITNOTTS Code of Conduct is based off the classic Bill and Ted quote &lt;em&gt;“Be Excellent To Each Other”&lt;/em&gt;. I could not be prouder of our members and 
how much they live and breathe this ethic. We helped each other. We helped others. We had a good time and made sure everyone around us was having 
a good time too. The rest of Nottingham must have a similar ethic as our stickers disappeared quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot happened while we were coding. If I were to cover it all this would become a novel. In summary - the hot chocolate was addictive, the company couldn’t have been better and the volunteers are world class. If you haven’t done Hack24 before, you should sign up for next year. In my three years I have joined a group of strangers, gone with a group organised at work and, this year, gone with people I wanted to get to know better. Every year I have managed to make new friends,
learn and laugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally the air horn sounded and it was time to make our videos. Luckily, Helen is a video queen! Helen, Laura and Elsa set up a story board and plan (this was while I was doing some last minute code pre-airhorn). They decided that we should use our app as a means of showing what it was all about, which meant running around Nottingham doing bonkers things and tweeting about it. If it hasn’t been removed yet you can view Team Totally Triumphant Bodacious Babes entry here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 30%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;205&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cTkEdTHDec8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the video had been submitted we had a couple of hours to waste while the judging was done. We then met up again for the awards ceremony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-results&quot;&gt;The Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all not only did the WITNOTTS teams do well, but some teams containing our members did as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Team Wild Garlic, Basil, Olive Oil, Pine Nuts &amp;amp; a Pinch of Salt &amp;amp; Pepper won two challenges: Esendex and Packed Pixels.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Team Totally Triumphant Bodacious Babes came second in the Cronofy challenge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WITNOTTS members Samathy and Alex’s team won the Unidays challenge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:80%; margin-left: 8%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-03-24/prizes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Winning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to lie - I was ECSTATIC that we won something. I couldn’t stop giggling for a long time afterwards purely due to the shock. Add on to the fact it was a model Delorean… well anyone who has been to WITNOTTS or seen me talk knows how much I love a good ol’ cult film reference. I don’t think any of us expected to get a prize so after all our toil, we were overjoyed to have won something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best result in my opinion though is that we had ladies in our teams that hadn’t been to many tech events and for which this was their first Hack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only are they planning to go to Hack24 2018, but have also been asking about other events in Nottingham and have been inspired to complete tech 
related projects. Getting people inspired by tech and to join in with the greater tech community is what makes all this worthwhile. Bringing more people into it, strengthening it &amp;amp; making it thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.technottingham.com/&quot;&gt;Tech Nottingham&lt;/a&gt; for building a welcoming tech family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-hack24-blogs&quot;&gt;Other Hack24 Blogs:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@LittleHelli/being-excellent-to-each-other-at-hack-24-bf3a1a188880#.ez70or21a&quot;&gt;Helen Clark - Being excellent to each other at Hack24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hack24.co.uk/blog/2017/3/23/hack24-2017-big-dreams-big-hacks-big-weekend?utm_content=buffer9780a&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;amp;utm_campaign=buffer&quot;&gt;Emma Seward - Hack24 2017: Big dreams, big hacks, big weekend&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mfyu.co.uk/post/hack-24-2017-live-blog&quot;&gt;Matt Brunt - HACK 24: 2017 LIVE BLOG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/hack242017-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/hack242017-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Error! Error!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;An assessment of error levels and what they mean.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are going to explore different levels of error, what they mean and when they should be used. Before we begin, there is a disclaimer: in my opinion logging is very important - but so is avoiding noise. I prefer logs that have a purpose and are going to be used. If I can’t use it or
act on it at any time, it’s not getting logged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is based off what I have learnt and my experience using logs as a developer. I’m currently using these levels in C# using Serilog, so this is where they will probably most applicable but the concepts will be made as generic as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;basic-error-levels&quot;&gt;Basic Error levels&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different levels available for logging including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;1. FATAL
2. ERROR
3. WARN
4. INFO
5. DEBUG
6. TRACE 
7. VERBOSE
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what do these mean and when should you use them? For consistent and effective logging this is something that should be agreed on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fatal&quot;&gt;FATAL&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE WORLD IS ENDING! This is for the worst of the very worst situation. This is for situations which force the application to close. As such their use should be very rare, if used at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:300px; margin-left: 30%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img//2017-03-11/fatal.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Fatal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;error&quot;&gt;ERROR&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is for something that has gone wrong that will not force the application to close but it will cause issues. These are for logging errors that could cause the operation to close, but can also be used for issues that don’t cause an application to close (i.e logging a 500 from a request). 
It is for any problems that require immediate intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;warn&quot;&gt;WARN&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is for problems that do not require immediate intervention, but that may cause issues or peculiarities at some point. It provides information but it isn’t something to act upon. The application continues even if it’s full behaviour isn’t quite as expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I wouldn’t use this level of logging, as if it’s not actionable, people won’t pay attention to it. Why not throw an error where the problem occurs, or if possible, guard against the possibility of their being an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is used however. An example given in &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2031163/when-to-use-the-different-log-levels&quot;&gt;reference 2&lt;/a&gt; is for logging bad login attempts. This could be used to assess problems in user experience. Something to consider is there are other tools that could be used for this purpose effectively. Is logging right for this use case?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;info&quot;&gt;INFO&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information level of logging is generally used for things you want to know about but that don’t cause your application to crash. There is a lot of confusion between the difference between information and debug, the principle I work by is that if it information that would be informative in production, log it as information. There is a careful balance that needs to be achieved however. You want to avoid noise, but be informative. For example, if you receive a 500 from an api, log it. Maybe don’t log all teh information corresponding to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing to consider when logging to production is the content of the information. You do not want to log sensitive or identifying information about customers for instance. Internal ID’s would be fine as you can track information without revealing anything you don’t intend to. Logs are not a secure place for storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information logs are also important in some systems as centralised logging can be used to build up monitoring. Logs and dashboards can be used to see early signs of different types of issues and for fine tuning. You can base your monitoring off centralised logging, and in a production system, the information logging would appropriate for this. It could be argued again that other tools can be used for such measurements. There are no fixed formula’s for how to use these different logging levels. I find this useful, but there are alternative ways of tackling this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;debug&quot;&gt;DEBUG&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Debug level is there to help diagnose issues. Again, some developers choose not to use this level of log at all, or filter it out. In my experience, the debug level has been useful for logging certain information about the application while fixing issues. I have seen it used (and used it myself) for logging information such as the elapsed time of a request or time of storing something to a database. The reason I keep this in the logs is so that it can be used in dashboards to assess performance, potentially help work out issues or see signs that something is going wrong / slowly in a component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;trace--verbose&quot;&gt;TRACE / VERBOSE&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Trace or Verbose level of logging is often used for very detailed level logging. For example it can be used to log user input. Often these logs do not live for long. They are put in to fix an issue and then are removed. This is to reduce the amount of noise thrown into the logs. Its been mentioned many times, but you don’t want to log something you don’t use as it will just cause fatigue and excess logging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the Trace level is not a level of logging I personally have used much. I can definitely see how it could be useful if used with discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-conclusion&quot;&gt;In conclusion..&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned throughout, how to use logging levels is not something that is completely concrete. In this article, I have explored my interpretation of what the levels mean and how to use them. This is from how I would use them in my job as a developer, but also from reading other peoples usage. Please send me any resources on the topic, or experiences that you have found useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align:center; width:300px; margin-left: 30%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2017-03-11/end.gif&quot; alt=&quot;End&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;Lets Talk About Logging - Dave Cheney&quot;&gt;https://dave.cheney.net/2015/11/05/lets-talk-about-logging&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;StackOverflow - Logging Levels&quot;&gt;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2031163/when-to-use-the-different-log-levels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;StackOverflow - Logging Levels 2&quot;&gt;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/7839565/logging-levels-logback-rule-of-thumb-to-assign-log-levels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/errorlevels-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/errorlevels-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>My First NDC</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My experience of being a volunteer at NDC London 2017.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ndc-london.com/&quot;&gt;NDC&lt;/a&gt; has been built up in my head as this awesome, magical conference ever since Moreton came back from it two years ago. Part of this was because he came back an excited kid, telling all these stories of the amazing time he had; part was because I thought it would be a long time before I could afford to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I learnt the amazing thing about being cheeky. The best thing that can happen is that you can have a grand adventure. The worst thing that could happen is that you hear the word “no”. I reached out to the world and asked how I could go even though I was skint. Thanks to twitter (particularly &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/khellang&quot;&gt;@khellang&lt;/a&gt;) I was told about the possibility of volunteering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-1---training&quot;&gt;Day 1 - training&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I was very nervous walking towards the ExCel. I didn’t really know what I was in for. After meeting the crew and organisers those worries  went out the window. We got shown the area, given our t-shirts and shown what we would be needed to do&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i64.tinypic.com/2cnfbpv.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;NDC Tee&quot; title=&quot;NDC Tee&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After training, one of the other volunteers and I walked back to the Travelodge. That would be the last good nights sleep I would have for a few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-conference&quot;&gt;The Conference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke a 6.30am ready for my first day at NDC. Put on my rockin’ NDC Crew Tee and walked to ExCel in the dark. The first part of the morning involved unpacking the free hoodies for the attendees and doing various other jobs. After the attendees had been checked in, all volunteers got to attend the keynote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now NDC is the biggest conference I have been too. The keynote was about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.htbox.org/&quot;&gt;Humanitarian Toolbox&lt;/a&gt;, which if you haven’t heard of it, you should click that link. Do code that’s good for the soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole set up was impressive. The stalls, people, food… it was all impressive. Volunteering at NDC is a really good deal as well. I’m not going through the whole conference experience but as a volunteer you spend half the day taking care of a room and the other half doing what you want. Taking care of the room involves making sure the speaker is happy, counting the votes and reporting them back and giving the speaker their gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first day, I worked the afternoon. The first talk I attended was Patterns for application development with ASP.NET Core by Damian Edwards adn David Fowler. It was a great first talk to attend. They were enthusiastic, really knew their topic and note only did I learn a lot but I was buzzing with excitement afterwards. Teh day continued in the same vein. I watched Scott Allen’s talk on ASP.NET Core and then my first shift started. The first room I had to look after was room 5, and as such the first speaker I kept an eye out for was Mathew McLoughlin. Being nervous, I arrived a bit early but that was fine because it meant I got to talk to him a bit. This not only calmed my nerves about the volunteer work, but he told me a a lot about how he got into speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great thing about volunteering is that you end up seeing talks you might not otherwise have seen. I saw some great talks. That afternoon alone I heard more about data and Docker, caching, and about process involved in delivering projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the end of the first day, I went on the evening boat cruise on the Thames.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i66.tinypic.com/2libxc1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Boat Trip&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aboard the Dixie Queen, a memorable night was had. Volunteers, speakers and attendees all went on this trip. Getting to know strangers is great fun, and it’s so much easier when they are held captive on a boat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joking aside, I got to have a laugh with the volunteers, talked to some developers from Tombola about their stack, their experiences and the conference and have a casual drink with some of the speakers as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my first big conference alone, it was the perfect first night. Turned out everybody else was just another person wanting to learn, have a great time and have a bit too much to drink. Also, it was a boat on the Thames! It was beautiful (and cold).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After and eventful night, I was up again at 7am for another morning of volunteering at the conference. Did I mention I really, really love NDC? The range of talks, the people; it is all done right. I tried to do a mix of topics I would use at work and topics I had had no exposure to before. This has led to a strong interest in functional programming - we’ll see where that leads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Thursday night was the social. My favourite bit was the short talks by speakers on times they had messed up. Sounds cruel, but it’s a fun way to learn and reinforces the fact that all the people who are on the stage spouting knowledge bombs are just people who f*ck up sometimes too. This was followed by the hardest pub quiz I have ever taken part in. I am a nerd n00b. Seriously studying to up my game for next time as the amount of unusable nerd knowledge in that room… if I was wearing a hat I would take it off to everyone. Honestly, I left early because I was exhausted - but there was no chance for our team anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i64.tinypic.com/1zyuert.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pub Conf&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning was the last day of NDC. No time to get emotional though as the day was packed full with talks and rounding off with PubConf. I had been lucky the day before and won a ticket to PubConf from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://katacoda.com/&quot;&gt;KataKoda&lt;/a&gt; Twitter give away (cheers folks!) as I missed out on buying a ticket beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody was tired, hungover or both but the talks throughout the day was still a really high standard. I worked the morning, so got to relax for the afternoon. After attending a final few talks, eating my fill of the wide selection of food and taking a last sweep of the stalls, I dropped my stuff off at the hotel, I wandered back to ExCel to find someone to follow to PubConf. Yes I know I could have used Google Maps, but this way is more fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of the excellent people I got to know over the course of NDC and I travelled together to the venue. PubConf is the perfect ending to NDC. Jokey, unrecorded speedy presentations, music, food and beverages. It was the most surreal night of the week. I made memories which will last a lifetime and some friends as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-end&quot;&gt;The End…?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;before-ndc&quot;&gt;Before NDC:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was nervous. The not knowing what the experience was going to be like and worried it wasn’t going to live up to the hype I had built around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking at conferences was a “no”.  &lt;em&gt;It’s scary. I am too early in my career. It’s scary.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tech was interesting but not nearly as exciting as I used to find it. I was an eternal n00b but not in the good way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;after-ndc&quot;&gt;After NDC:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NDC lived up to all the hype. It’s an amazing experience. It’s not just about the learning experience but also about the community. Going to NDC was also great personally. Since NDC a week ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’ve already signed up for NDC Oslo as a volunteer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’m in the process of writing my first CFP - with help from people I met at NDC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being scared is not going to stop me again&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’ve had to try and lose ALL the weight gained from the excellent food&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with learning about some great technologies and re-igniting my passion or tech, it’s also been a big confidence builder. There are people I can reach out to about a range of things, technical and personal. There’s tonnes to learn and get excited about. Everybody is a n00b in some way and that is awesome. I have years to learn and get better as a developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NDC is good for you. It’s not great for your waistline.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/ndclondon-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/ndclondon-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Be A Great Engineer - WITConf, University of Birmingham</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My very first talk - speaking at the Women In Tech Conference 2.0 at The University of Birmingham.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-day&quot;&gt;About The Day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a 4.30am rise, train journey in, and one terrible coffee; I had arrived at the University of Birmingham.
I had been invited to speak at the Women In Tech 2.0 Conference. This is an event organised by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/oSTEM_bham&quot;&gt;oSTEM&lt;/a&gt; at Birmingham,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WISEatUoB&quot;&gt;WISE at Birmingham&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CSSBham&quot;&gt;CSS Birmingham&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my very first go at doing a public talk, and admittedly it took a lot of arm twisting by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TauOmicronMu&quot;&gt;Tom Goodman&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not the most confident at this kind of thing (despite what my online presence might suggest)
 but Tom is a wizard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all the day was great fun. I got to meet some smart people, eat way to much food and learn. The organisers were
 very sweet - pumping caffeine into me every moment and checking all the attendees were having a good time. It 
 was a really nice touch that they gave all the speakers a bunch of flowers too. I also enjoyed 
 having the opportunity to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Samathy_Barratt&quot;&gt;Samathy&lt;/a&gt; speak at the event. We have crossed paths occasionally
 but this was the first chance to get to know her well, and her talk was really well delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2016-11-12/speakers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;You will never stop learning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of the talk was not as bad as expected either. It is still scary. I didn’t trip and fall on my face. People 
 seemed to like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-talk---be-a-great-engineer&quot;&gt;The Talk - “Be A Great Engineer”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a cut down version of the talk I gave. Hopefully it translates well without the hand waving and gesturing.
I was going to share the slides alone, but there is nothing on them, so instead I have written it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;you-will-never-stop-learning&quot;&gt;You will never stop learning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2016-11-12/learning_slide.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;You will never stop learning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my favourite thing about being an engineer. There is an endless wealth of things to learn about. Even when you think you have the handle on a topic, new stuff will come out in the next ten minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s overwhelming. It’s exciting. It’s &lt;strong&gt;your&lt;/strong&gt; future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to be a great engineer? Study. This isn’t just reading the books and the blogs. This is attending hackathons, going to meetups, being part of your tech community, contributing to open source, practising with homebrew projects and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds like a lot but you don’t have to do it all. At hackathons and meetups, you can learn from people and find out about areas you wouldn’t normally be exposed to. By doing some code at home you can practice and try out new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t let it eat up your life, but if you are passionate about something chase it. Don’t be afraid to write a blog or do a talk if you learn something cool. Even if it’s something that isn’t “cool” but is useful, someone will probably benefit from it. The never ending cycle of knowledge sharing will continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;never-be-afraid-to-ask&quot;&gt;Never Be Afraid To Ask&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is &lt;strong&gt;NO SUCH THING AS A STUPID QUESTION&lt;/strong&gt;.  I know, cliché and who believes it; but it’s TRUE!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t understand something ask. If you think you could learn more in an area you are interested in, ask for resources. If you have forgotten something you got shown how to do 10 minutes before and don’t know where to look it up, ask someone to show you again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you will make mistakes. Sometimes you will so something wrong. That’s ok! When this happens, put your hands up, acknowledge that you’ve done something wrong. If you can’t fix it, ask for help. No one is judging you. Sit with them while they fix it and learn from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few things you shouldn’t do. One is to try to hide a mistake, especially if you can’t fix it.  Another is to pretend you understand something that you don’t. You are only cheating yourself out of the opportunity to learn. Honesty is the best policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;experience--intelligence&quot;&gt;Experience != Intelligence&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are lucky you will be surrounded by talented and more experienced developers than you. This is a great place to be, but it can also be hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These people have had YEARS to learn. Even if they have the same amount of experience, they may have focused on a different area from you and learnt about it to a further degree. Do not mistake their different experience to intelligence. You are smart. It’s likely you are learning at AT LEAST the same pace as the people you work with. You may even have some knowledge that your colleagues don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2016-11-12/Imposter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Imposter Syndrome&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other side to this is that you will work with people who forget what it’s like to be new. They might treat you like you know very little. Remind them that you are new to this and that they had to learn once too. There is a way to work with people that have more experience without feeling very small about yourself. If someone makes you feel small, that is something they need to work on to avoid doing. Even the most experienced developers can learn from the newest. This is all thanks again to the vast field we work on. In this field we all get different experiences, and exposure to different techniques. As such we can all learn from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;you-are-smart-enough-for-anything&quot;&gt;You Are Smart Enough For Anything.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You can be a great engineer. You can be a great engineer in any way you want to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, back end development has a crazy reputation for being complicated and mathsey which puts some people off. It’s really not. It requires logic, but that’s fun! If you get the opportunity, give it a try. You might be better at it than you know, and might enjoy it more than you can fathom. If you struggle with it, or don’t enjoy it, that’s fine. You tried it. You have a different preference or skill set. You will still benefit from the experience as you will have a better overview of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;even-though-sometimes-it-wont-feel-like-it&quot;&gt;Even Though Sometimes It Won’t Feel Like It&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2016-11-12/horo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Imposter Syndrome&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a common theme throughout these points. Some days you will feel on top of the world; while others, not so much. The self-doubt, the comparisons to other colleagues, the sometimes feeling alone. Turns out this is a thing. It’s called imposter syndrome. Want to know a secret - it’s common. It’s hard to fight, but together we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imposter syndrome is a huge topic, much to big to go into here. Part of it is feeling like a fraud. Like you aren’t as good as everyone around you. Feeling like you don’t deserve the position you’re in and that someone is going to realise how crap you are. It’s also feeling isolated from the people around you. That you can’t relate. Feeling like their experiences are completely unrelated to your circumstance, so you can’t judge if you will ever be as good as them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will happen, there is no real way of avoiding it. When you start to see someone else crumble, reach out to them. Point out the awesome job they are doing. Get them away from their desk and get them to grab a coffee, be a sympathetic and empathetic ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Together we can help each other. All of you can and will be great engineers, even if sometimes it won’t feel like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;you-can-do-anything&quot;&gt;You can do anything!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2016-11-12/wecandoit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Imposter Syndrome&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now the world is a bit scary. Knowing if you are going down the right path is not something that necessarily comes easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what? It’s not the end of the world. You might be good at one part of development and suck at another. I am working to be a great back-end engineer. Part of this is because I SUCK at front end engineering. You might not enjoy a certain challenge within engineering yet flourish in another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If after a few years, you aren’t enjoying being an engineer, there are many roles you can move into that don’t involve code and are still very rewarding. Don’t sink under the pressure. If you knew everything about your future, life would be dull. You will be great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;take-every-opportunity&quot;&gt;Take every opportunity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this unknown future, you will have the opportunity to do many great things. Some of them will seem alien and scary which might put you off. Some, you might think are beyond you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weigh up the advantages and disadvantages to these opportunities. Not just for your present role but what you might do in the future. Will you learn a new skill? Would it strengthen your knowledge in certain area? Is it just new and exciting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then think how it might benefit the company you work for. Exposure, recruitment etc. If the opportunity is something you may need funding for, your company is likely to help with these kinds of things, but sometimes you will need to put a case together for why it would benefit them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with anything if you can think of more costs than benefits, then the opportunity is not worthwhile. Just keep in mind that your fear of self-confidence shouldn’t be a negative. Ride that wave!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I say this like it is the easiest thing in the world. I know it’s not. Part of why I started Women In Tech in Nottingham was because I felt there was a need for it, that I could do it well and that it would help build upon the social skill of talking to strangers without looking at my own feet. Nine months later, here I am doing my very first talk. Talking to strangers, talking about a subject with confidence, being able to express myself clearly. All skills I will take back to my day to day job. All learnt from diving in the deep end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are advantages I didn’t even consider too. I’ve met great people, gone to places I would have never had the opportunity to going to, learnt more than what I considered I might do. It’s good to stick your middle finger up to fear, and profit from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dont-be-afraid-to-fight-back&quot;&gt;Don’t be afraid to fight back&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you know that you are all empowered, intelligent people who are going to be great in this industry and do things you never thought you would do. Sometimes, you will have to fight to make other people realise this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because people think they know what’s best for you, doesn’t mean they are right. If you  stand up for yourself, they will respect your honesty and drive. Be diplomatic though, don’t go in with unsupported arguments and expect the world. Most of the time, you know what is best for you. Have the confidence to stand up for what you want. This includes area of your work, pay-rises, promotions, going to conferences and other opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You are a valuable asset. A great engineer. Make sure the world knows it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/witconf-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/witconf-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Sonos Pi Project</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Using a Raspberry Pi to make vocal alerts on a Sonos based off output from Datadog.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about&quot;&gt;About&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a joint project between myself and my partner Moreton as our first attempt at using a RaspberryPi and test driving a Node.JS project. We both wanted to learn node and when I came up with the project idea as a piece of fun to help out the place I work at; it seemed like the perfect opportunity to learn Node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/2016-07-10/piOne.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pi&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iteration-one&quot;&gt;Iteration One&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the first iteration was to enable a vocal alert to be sounded on a Sonos speaker based on events set up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datadoghq.com&quot;&gt;DataDog&lt;/a&gt;. This was done forking the code from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jishi/node-sonos-http-api&quot;&gt;sonos-http-api&lt;/a&gt; to make a sonos server/api, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.voicerss.org/&quot;&gt;Voice RSS&lt;/a&gt; for the vocal mp3, writing our own code to write an API and the logic about what was to be said across the Sonos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We test drove our code, pairing using a red, green, refactor pattern. Once it was shown to be working, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ngrok.com&quot;&gt;ngrok&lt;/a&gt; was used to produce a secure url to configure a DataDog webhook to, using the webhook integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code for this can be found &lt;a href=&quot;href=&amp;quot;https://github.com/sonos-alerts&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; with all current instructions on how to work it. The DataDog details are currently not included.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/sonospi-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sonospi-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>NodeConf London</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overview of NodeConf London 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;agenda&quot;&gt;Agenda&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://london.nodeconf.com/&quot;&gt;NodeConf London&lt;/a&gt; included the following talks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nodebotanist&quot;&gt;Kassandra Perch&lt;/a&gt; - Robots, code and people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nikhilaravi&quot;&gt;Nikhila Ravi&lt;/a&gt; - Server-less architecture in the wild&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/substack&quot;&gt;James Halliday&lt;/a&gt; - The disintermediated web&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/codepo8&quot;&gt;Christian Heilmann&lt;/a&gt; - Making ES6 happen with ChakraCore and Node&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cjihrig&quot;&gt;Colin Ihrig&lt;/a&gt; - State of Node.js Core&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wa7son&quot;&gt;Thomas Watson&lt;/a&gt; - It goes to eleven&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nexxylove&quot;&gt;Emily Rose&lt;/a&gt; - How I learned to stop worrying&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sublimino&quot;&gt;Andrew Martin&lt;/a&gt; - Avoiding release paralysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/janl&quot;&gt;Jan Lehnardt&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; - Kill all humans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lucamaraschi&quot;&gt;Luca Maraschi&lt;/a&gt; - SWIMming in the microservices ocean&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/matthew1000&quot;&gt;Matt Clark&lt;/a&gt; - Node.js that is hugely reliable, fast, and scalable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ones-to-watch&quot;&gt;Ones To Watch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the talks should be watched and are available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL0CdgOSSGlBYnHAl_DZoy9BWvdVQjNKE2&quot;&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;. Below is a list of a few of my favourites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;nikhila-ravi---server-less-architecture-in-the-wild&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;href=&amp;quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SwJUH3Le91s&quot;&gt;Nikhila Ravi&lt;/a&gt; - Server-less architecture in the wild:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An insightful and intelligent talk going through using a “serveless” architecture. This talk includes demonstrating the creation of a “serverless jukebox” including a live demonstration of the work available on Github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;christian-heilmann---making-es6-happen-with-chakracore-and-node&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jHTSCXQ3-hU&quot;&gt;Christian Heilmann&lt;/a&gt; - Making ES6 happen with ChakraCore and Node:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk is not only enlightening but hilarious. Christian Heilman is a highly entertaining speaker who is clearly knowledgeable and passionate about what he is talking about. Even as a JS newbie I could follow what he was talking about and instantly started looking into ChakraCore as soon as I got home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;kassandra-perch---robots-code-and-people&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=edYnouynBxg&quot;&gt;Kassandra Perch&lt;/a&gt; - Robots, code and people:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not the most technical talk of the lot - but Kassandra spoke to things we all recognise with awesome quotes and energy. She explores why we code, and the importance of the want for learning and the enjoyment of projects. She then goes on to talk about the importance of creating a space that’s inclusive to everyone in order to   not destroying the potential to learn and make new and great things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;andrew-martin---avoiding-release-paralysis&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vOMcJ3kRMVo&quot;&gt;Andrew Martin&lt;/a&gt; - Avoiding release paralysis:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to learn about free technologies to help you with Continuous Integration, Continuous Delivery and Continuous Deployment? Then this is the talk you need to watch. Also it’s giphy-tastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;luca-maraschi---swimming-in-the-microservices-ocean&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TK7eeL3RQ4M&quot;&gt;Luca Maraschi&lt;/a&gt; - SWIMming in the microservices ocean:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering this talk was finished less than an hour before it was delivered, it was well presented and the content interesting. Want to know more about how companies like Uber operate? Watch this talk for a few insights..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;matt-clark---nodejs-thats-hugely-reliable-fast-and-scalable&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pxmXiKlh5OU&quot;&gt;Matt Clark&lt;/a&gt; - Node.js thats hugely reliable, fast, and scalable:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lessons learned from the BBC about producing fast, reliable and scalable Node apps. These principles also relate highly to working in a microservices style architecture. This talk is a great insight into the workings of certain BBC sites, but also how to avoid potential dangers while developing Node apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content of NodeConf London was incredibly high quality, and those involved in making it possible were extremely professional. The volunteers were friendly and informative even though they had their hands full with Twitter, Gitter and all the other possible communication channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some set themes to the talks. Microservices, Docker, high-quality testing were all frequently mentioned as important for creating production quality Node apps. I left feeling inspired to investigate numerous things including Server-less architectures, how other companies use Docker in production in greater detail and using Blue-Green architectures to assist in testing on live environments with minimal risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, despite the fantastic Code of Conduct - there was a bit of .NET bashing, which as a .NET dev I thought was sad. My interest in Node is recent but I also love working with C# and would hate to think I can’t like both. It was also a shame that thought there was a diverse range of speakers, the panel at the end of the event were all men giving their answers. It would have been nice to have seen more diversity there, and to see if there were any difference in opinion to some fo the questions asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, NodeConf is a great conference. I encourage everyone to keep an eye out on Nearforms future events.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/nodeconf-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/nodeconf-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Microservices Day</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overview of Microservices Day London 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;common-themes&quot;&gt;Common Themes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/&quot;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/&quot;&gt;Cloud / AWS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/CanaryRelease.html&quot;&gt;Canary Testing / Release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/BlueGreenDeployment.html&quot;&gt;Blue-Green Deployment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~asdas/research/dsn02-swim.pdf&quot;&gt;SWIM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;agenda&quot;&gt;Agenda&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://microservicesday.com/#agenda&quot;&gt;Agenda&lt;/a&gt; of the day included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fgeorge52&quot;&gt;Fred George&lt;/a&gt; - How to enable organizations to go faster&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/adrian_trenaman&quot;&gt;Adrian Trenaman&lt;/a&gt; - Fighting the Good Fight at the Hot Gates of Micro-Services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rjrodger&quot;&gt;Richard Rodger&lt;/a&gt; - Solving service discovery: how Node.js microservices can find each other without a registry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jasonmelo&quot;&gt;Jason Melo&lt;/a&gt; - Microliths: how to avoid traps in your stack and your culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/clifcunn&quot;&gt;Clifton Cunningham&lt;/a&gt; - Micro-transformation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/anne_e_currie&quot;&gt;Anne Currie&lt;/a&gt; - Microservices and Containers. How much faster than a VM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/valgog&quot;&gt;Valentine Gogichashvili&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp;  Fabian Wollert - Data integration in the world of microservices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ones-to-watch&quot;&gt;Ones To Watch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the talks are available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL0CdgOSSGlBZkM4ZSGO0fjkNTXEIteQy9&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a list of a few of my favourites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;richard-rodger---solving-service-discovery-nodejs-microservices-without-a-registry&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9VC6YeQeZVk&quot;&gt;Richard Rodger&lt;/a&gt; - Solving service discovery: Node.js microservices without a registry:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk went through the lessons learnt by Nearform in there 5 years of working with microservices. Richard first stated that automated deployment is essential to be able to work efficiently with microservices. He also went on to praise &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Netflix/eureka&quot;&gt;Netflix Eureka&lt;/a&gt; as an example of intelligent load balancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argued that ‘service discovery’ is now an anti-pattern and that we should make message first class citizens, using them to define patterns. In this it should not matter where a message ends up or how it got there, only that a service is interested in something it contains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to discuss that each service should have a local view of itself, but there should be a self-updating global view using
                            &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~asdas/research/dsn02-swim.pdf&quot;&gt;SWIM&lt;/a&gt; (Scalable Weakly-consistent Infection-style Process Group Membership Protocol). In this each service pings random services. This knowledge is then shared on to the next set of pings, and so the process continues. Using this process we can see which services are up and which are not. At convergence you get complete knowledge of the entire system and all this happens in milliseconds. This is useful for scalability and composability.  &lt;br /&gt;
An example of the implementation of a microservices architecture using Node.JS written by Richard can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/senecajs/ramanujan&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This is a Twitter like app that uses the Seneca microservices framework that is also a good example of the SWIM protocol for peer-to-peer discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fred-george---how-to-enable-organizations-to-go-faster&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WKTtnVb83mQ&quot;&gt;Fred George&lt;/a&gt; - How to enable organizations to go faster:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fred George is a pretty well known speaker, so admittedly I was excited to see him speak. In this talk he explored the hot topics surrounding microservices, which pretty much covered the common themes throughout the whole day. He then went on to discuss the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cynefin_Framework&quot;&gt;Cynefin Framework&lt;/a&gt; and how it acn be used to judge how profitable a solution to a problem may be as well as whether a company should use traditional or non-traditional methods to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to discuss the 5 points which can help an organisation progress:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand your problem.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If it is a complex problem, you need to be able to fail fast as “experimentation drive innovation”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If it is a complex problem, re-think interactions - consider the interaction with customer at feature level rather than story level.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measure what matters - expose developers to business success metrics, customer retention, clicks. Make the impact of their work visible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mitigate organisational inhibitors - this includes over-specialisation and too many managers, none of which have a clear overall picture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred George also explored the hierarchy of development. Thought I saw his vision here, personally I am still a strong advocate for a flat structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A flat structure encourages the idea that everyone’s view is valid, as the only difference between a senior / junior is their experiences, and as such both can have a valid point of view. Fred explored a much more hierarchical structure which rewarded knowledge - but personally I find such structures can introduce bad attitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jason-melo---microliths-how-to-avoid-traps-in-your-stack-and-your-culture&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UAJuYs5PNqk&quot;&gt;Jason Melo&lt;/a&gt; - Microliths: how to avoid traps in your stack and your culture&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the term ‘Microlith’ which Jason used to refer to tightly coupled microservices. This is definitely a danger when moving from a monolith to a microservices architecture. In this talk Jason Melo discussed the journey from monolith to microservice in the following phases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;phase-1a---cultural-mindshift-embrace-the-chaos&quot;&gt;Phase 1a - Cultural mindshift: EMBRACE THE CHAOS!&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is involved in DevOps and it is not an individuals role! There will be well defined service ownership and LOADS of databases! Multiple run times!
These are factors which some may have difficulty with in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;phase-1b---strangling-the-monolith&quot;&gt;Phase 1b - Strangling the monolith:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams control their services with domain boundaries, guard rails and build pipelines. You can expect very high amounts of network chattiness dependent on synchronous REST. Elegant service discovery can make this process more smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;phase-2---event-messaging-over-rest--logging-and-analytics&quot;&gt;Phase 2 - Event Messaging over REST + Logging and Analytics:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decoupling the microlith us difficult and investment in logging is VERY important. A transaction tracer can also be useful for seeing flow and can be used in conjunction with logs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elastic.co/products&quot;&gt;Elasticsearch, Logstash and Kibana&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&quot;http://kafka.apache.org/&quot;&gt;Kafka&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://spark.apache.org/&quot;&gt;Spark&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/Welcome.html&quot;&gt;S3&lt;/a&gt; are all examples of aggregated logging solutions. If you are using Blue-Green deployment, you can do real time log analytics on deployment using the same analytics platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;phase-3---scheduling-and-orchestrationb&quot;&gt;Phase 3 - Scheduling and Orchestration:&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jenkins.io/&quot;&gt;Jenkins&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/products/docker-universal-control-plane&quot;&gt;Docker UCP&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.docker.com/swarm/&quot;&gt;Swarm&lt;/a&gt; on AWS, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/cloudformation/&quot;&gt;Cloud Formation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ansible.com/&quot;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt; - you need to work hard at getting persistence and scaling right! These can run distributed data streaming, messaging and analytics pipelines seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting seeing how another company has approached the monolith to microservices journey and the tools they found useful. There seems to be many variations of this journey but a lot of the same difficulties are faced in each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, for a free event, the quality of the speakers was supprisingly high. The venue was fantastic, the staff friendly and the general vibe was very open. As a conference, I would recommend it for both those wanting to explore moving into a microservices architecture and those that are established. It is good to learn from other companies wins and mistakes, but also there are a lot of practices and tools that may be useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microservices Day did feel a bit like a practice for NodeConf, but it was free so I cannot complain about that. The talks all followed similar themes and towards the end of the day it started to feel like you had heard the same thing three times over - but I guess that it what comes from having a small area to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting to hear about how companies had dealt with the transition to a microservices architecture and it was the first time I had come across SWIM protocol which I found a particularly interesting concept. The use of Docker in production, and the way in which companies were testing new functionality was slightly different from what I have experienced. There were a few things throughout the day that I think are worthy of further investigation, with the aim of eventually trying out some of them in my own work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/microservicesday-post/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/microservicesday-post/</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
